Curriculum Vitae Nils Lukas

November 19, 2023 University of Waterloo, Ontario, Canada nilslukas.github.io / nlukas@uwaterloo.ca

#### Research Overview

My research focuses on threats in deploying deep neural networks, encompassing (i) controlling misuse from untrustworthy users, (ii) model integrity with untrustworthy data, and (iii) privacy concerns from untrustworthy models that leak sensitive information. My contributions include studying privacy attacks on language models, defenses against data poisoning, and watermarking methods to control misuse.

## Education

Ph.D. in Computer Science, University of Waterloo, Canada Jan 2019 - Jan 2024

Advisor: Prof. Florian Kerschbaum

Thesis: "Analyzing Threats of Large-Scale Machine Learning Systems"

M.Sc. in Computer Science, RWTH-Aachen, Germany May 2016 - Oct 2018

Advisor: Prof. Stefan Decker

Thesis: "Secure Inference for Deep Neural Networks" **B.Sc. in Computer Science**, RWTH-Aachen, Germany

Oct 2012 - Apr 2016

**Experience** 

Research Intern, Microsoft Research May 2022 - Aug 2022

Topic: Privacy in Large Language Models. See our IEEE S&P'23 publication.

**Instructional Advisor**, University of Waterloo Sep 2021 - Dec 2021

Course: Object-Oriented Software Development

**Co-Instructor**, Group on Information Systems at the RWTH-Aachen Oct 2017 - Mar 2018

Course: Data-Driven Medicine

#### **Conference Publications**

### [USENIX'23]

AR: 29% (422/1444)

## [IEEE S&P'23]

AR: 17% (195/1147)

₱ Distinguished Contribution Award at Microsoft MLADS

#### [IEEE S&P'22]

AR: 14.5% (147/1012)

## [ICLR'21]

AR: 28.7% (860/2997)

T Spotlight Award

## [IH&MMSEC'21]

AR: 40.0% (128/318)

# [ACSAC'20]

AR: 20.9% (104/497)

## [IEEE EuroS&P'20]

AR: 20.9% (39/187)

**Nils Lukas** and Florian Kerschbaum. *PTW: Pivotal Tuning Watermarking for Pre-Trained Image Generators*, 32nd USENIX Security Symposium, 2023, [pdf]

**Nils Lukas**, Ahmed Salem, Robert Sim, Shruti Tople, Lukas Wutschitz, Santiago Zanella-Béguelin. *Analyzing Leakage of Personally Identifiable Information in Language Models*, 44th IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy, 2023, [pdf]

**Nils Lukas**, Edward Jiang, Xinda Li, Florian Kerschbaum. *Sok: How Robust is Image Classification Deep Neural Network Watermarking?*, 43rd IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy, 2022, [pdf]

**Nils Lukas**, Yuxuan Zhang, Florian Kerschbaum. *Deep Neural Network Finger-printing by Conferrable Adversarial Examples*, The Ninth International Conference on Learning Representations, 2021 [pdf]

Masoumeh Shafieinejad, **Nils Lukas**, Jiaqi Wang, Xinda Li, Florian Kerschbaum. *On the Robustness of Backdoor-based Watermarking in Deep Neural Networks*, Proceedings of the 2021 ACM Workshop on Information Hiding and Multimedia Security, 2021, [pdf]

Rasoul Akhavan Mahdavi, Thomas Humphries, Bailey Kacsmar, Simeon Krastnikov, **Nils Lukas**, John A Premkumar, Masoumeh Shafieinejad, Simon Oya, Florian Kerschbaum, Erik-Oliver Blass. *Practical Over-Threshold Multi-Party Private Set Intersection*, Annual Computer Security Applications Conference, 2020, pp. 772-783, [pdf]

Bailey Kacsmar, Basit Khurram, **Nils Lukas**, Alexander Norton, Masoumeh Shafieinejad, Zhiwei Shang, Yaser Baseri, Maryam Sepehri, Simon Oya, Florian Kerschbaum. *Differentially private two-party set operations*, 2020 IEEE European Symposium on Security and Privacy (EuroS&P), 2020, pp. 390-404 [pdf]

Curriculum Vitae Nils Lukas

# **Journal Publications**

[AIP'18]

Pascal Richter, Gregor Heiming, **Nils Lukas**, Martin Frank. *SunFlower: A new solar tower simulation method for use in field layout optimization*, AIP Conference Proceedings, Volume 2033, Issue 1, 2018, [pdf]

## **Under Submission**

| 2023 | <b>Nils Lukas</b> , Abdulrahman Diaa, Lucas Fenaux, Florian Kerschbaum. <i>Leveraging Optimization for Adaptive Attacks on Image Watermarks</i> , 2023, [pdf]   |
|------|---|
| 2023 | Benjamin Schneider, <b>Nils Lukas</b> , Florian Kerschbaum. <i>Universal Backdoor Attacks</i> , 2023.   |
| 2023 | <b>Nils Lukas</b> , Florian Kerschbaum. <i>Pick your Poison: Undetectability versus Robustness in Data Poisoning Attacks against Deep Image Classification</i> , 2023, [pdf]  |
| 2023 | Abdulrahman Diaa, Lucas Fenaux, Thomas Humphries, Marian Dietz, Faezeh Ebrahimianghazani, Bailey Kacsmar, Xinda Li, <b>Nils Lukas</b> , Rasoul Akhavan Mahdavi, Simon Oya, Ehsan Amjadian, Florian Kerschbaum. <i>Fast and Private Inference of Deep Neural Networks by Co-designing Activation Functions</i> , 2023, [pdf] |
| 2023 | Rasoul Mahdavi, <b>Nils Lukas</b> , Faezeh Ebrahimianghazani, Thomas Humphries, Bailey<br>Kacsmar, John Premkumar, Xinda Li, Simon Oya, Ehsan Amjadian, Florian Kerschbaum  |

## **Tutorials**

[ESWC'18] Nils Lukas, Oya Beyan, Ali Hasnain. Privacy-Preserving Information Extraction with Bloom Filters, European Semantic Web Conference, Greece, 2018, [web]

PEPSI: Practically Efficient Private Set Intersection in the Unbalanced Setting, 2023.

## **Awards and Honors**

| 2023 | Best Poster Award - Presentation with David R. Cheriton [300 CAD]             |
|------|---|
|      | Distinguished Contribution Award - Microsoft-internal 2023 MLADS conference   |
| 2022 | David R. Cheriton Scholarship - 2-year award [20,000 CAD]                     |
|      | Outstanding Reviewer - International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML'22) |
| 2019 | Best Poster Award - Cybersecurity and Privacy Institute (CPI) [1,000 CAD]     |
| 2018 | Excellence Graduation - Master's degree                                       |
| 2016 | KU Global Scholarship - Semester abroad, Korea University [1.2 million KRW]   |
| 2014 | MOGAM Scholarship - Semester abroad, Yonsei University, Korea [3,000 EUR]     |

# **University Service**

2022 Student Board Member - Cybersecurity and Privacy Institute (CPI)
School Advisory Committee on Appointments (SACA) Liaison - CrySP lab

# **Academic Service**

| 2024 | Reviewer, The Web Conference (ACM TheWebConf'24)                                  |
|------|---|
|      | Reviewer, International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR'24)          |
| 2023 | Program Chair, Artifact Evaluation, Computer and Communications Security (CCS'23) |
|      | Reviewer, Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS'23)                      |
|      | Session Chair, The 44th IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (IEEE S&P'23)      |
|      | Reviewer, Recent Advances in Intrusion Detection (RAID'23)                        |
|      | Reviewer, The 23rd Privacy Enhancing Technologies Symposium (PETS'23)             |
| 2022 | Reviewer, International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML'22)                  |
|      | Reviewer, The 22nd Privacy Enhancing Technologies Symposium (PETS'22)             |
|      | Reviewer, Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS'22)                      |
| 2021 | Reviewer, The 21st Privacy Enhancing Technologies Symposium (PETS'21)             |